[Music]
Stanford University all right we were
talking about something called t-duality
t-duality
was very very important to the history
of the mathematical developments of
string theory let's go back over it
again and discuss it a little more fully
and then I want to tell you how it led
to the concept of D brains and how D
brains have become something of a
mathematical tool for studying quantum
field theories the kind of quantum field
theories but have nothing to do gravity
but the kind of quantum field theories
that we use in a day-to-day basis to
understand hadrian's quantum
electrodynamics and even quantum field
theories that are interesting to
condensed matter physicists we won't get
to all of this so obviously we won't get
to this today but I'll just try to give
you some picture of what it's about all
right we we imagine that there was some
compact directions of compact means
these small ones which we rolled up the
simplicity I will imagine that the
compactification is toroidal on Torah in
other words not necessarily
two-dimensional torus a one-dimensional
torus is a circle or a line interval
with the endpoints being identified a
two-dimensional torus is a non erect a
parallelogram doesn't have to be
straight the parallelogram with opposite
sides identified a three-dimensional
torus is a cube or not necessarily a
cube but a parallelepiped thank you a
parallelepiped with opposite faces
identified at this point in that point
this point and that point and you know
in front in the back so in general in
any dimension the concept of a torus is
a well-defined concept and those are the
easiest cases to study those are the
easiest cases to study in these cases of
course supplement on top of this is the
ordinary four dimensions of space-time
so this is what's present at every point
of space-time ordinary space-time there
are other directions that we can move in
or that somebody small enough can move
in and that's the setup now let's focus
on one particular place in space-time
and ask what could be there a particle
can be there but now let's zero in and
zoom in and ask what that particle looks
like on scales which are so small that
these compact directions become visible
so let's start with a simple picture
that we had just to just to get started
we imagine one large direction and one
small direction the small direction now
would be called a circle a circle not
because it's embedded in two dimensions
and looks like a circle but just because
its head études tail that when you go
around come back and come back to the
same place all right so that's our
space-time where as time I don't know
time is add time into it time is not
drawn on the blackboard this is pure
space okay in this case two-dimensional
but if you like we can generalize at the
higher dimensions the compact directions
become tore I the non compact directions
the big ones just become our three
dimensions of space so however many
dimensions of space we want
now in string theory particles are
strings let's take the case of not all
string theories are the same they're
different from each other
but there's a fairly small
classification of them the strings
theories that I'm interested in right
now have only closed strings we're going
to come back to what happens when you
have open strings in a little while but
for the moment only closed strings no
end points that's number one so they're
like rubber bands they're like rubber
bands here they aren't closed and
furthermore that what we would call we
call oriented oriented means that
there's an intrinsic dis difference
between going around the string in one
direction rather than in the other
direction it's mathematically like a
rubber band in which on the rubber band
we drew a series of arrows to indicate
direction around and we'll keep track of
that orientation an example of what that
orientation would say is when the string
splits little splits like this it will
split into two strings with the same
orientation on the blackboard
so in that sense orientation is
preserved for these strings they
remember a sense of which now of course
that doesn't mean that they're in
equivalent I mean it may there may be a
symmetry and the sense that a string
with the opposite orientation may have
all the same properties but what it does
mean is that you can compare two strings
to see whether they have the same
orientation or the opposite orientation
to bring same with electric charge a
positive electric charges behave exactly
the same way as well as negative
electric charges in in that for example
if you replaced in the real world every
electron by a positron every proton by
an antiproton and with it every Neutron
by an anti Neutron
chemistry would remain exactly the same
or at least to a very very high
precision would remain unchanged so in
that sense plus charges are identical to
minus charges but you can tell the
difference between the plotter you can
know you can't tell the difference
between a plus charge and a minus charge
but if you have two charges you can tell
whether they are the same or opposite
how to see whether they attract or repel
you can't tell whether they're both plus
or whether they're both - but you can't
tell okay so the same is true of
oriented strings that they have a sense
of orientation if you replaced every
string in string theory by a string of
the opposite orientation the theory
would be the same but if you have two
strings you can tell whether they're the
same orientation of your episode let's
just call them oriented strings then you
can wrap them well you can do two things
you can have a string which is not wound
around become eight some compact
direction there it is it is drawn on the
surface of the two-dimensional world
here it's free to move it can move in
this direction or it can move around so
it can have momentum and that momentum
can be along the direction of the large
directions or it can be along the short
directions or it can be a combination of
both it can when I say it has momentum
we can think of that as motion and it
can move this way it could move this way
or it can even move in a in a helical
pattern like that having both components
of momentum the components of the
momentum in the short directions and the
finite compact directions are quantized
they are quantized in integer multiples
of the inverse radius or the inverse
friends the distance around the clothes
called a cycle around the clothes cycle
do the streets have to go all the way
around the cylinder can it be like
computer this one isn't going all the
ways around
what do you call it I thought they went
from like zero to two five in close in
what space Wow no this is not Sigma this
is some X this could be X we could call
this direction Y around here
let's space that's real space Sigma is
just a parameter which changes along the
string it's just naming the points along
the string you have a rubber band and
the rubber band is composed of molecules
okay the molecules can be named the
first molecule is Harry then George and
Fred then Sara and so forth that's Sigma
its naming the particles as you go
around the string okay and if the string
is closed
yeah then Sigma comes back to itself
yeah the size has to be the same what
does the size of the compact Direction
have to be the same at every place in
the long direction we'll come to that
the answer's no no it does not but we'll
come to that okay so Sigma varies along
here along the string and it goes from 0
to 2 pi but that has nothing whatever to
do with whether the string is wrapped
around space so yeah think of it I'm
sorry I didn't bring a rubber band think
of a rubber band we're on the surface of
the rubber band we've marked off Sigma
equals 0 Sigma equals a small number or
twice the small number as we
around the rubber band here it is rubber
band and we mark off points on the
rubber band that's Sigma that Sigma has
nothing to do with whether I wrap the
rubber band around my wrist or not it's
always there it's Sigma it goes around
once as the string goes as we follow the
string around its own shape Sigma goes
from 0 to 2 pi it's a completely
separate question of whether the string
is wrapped around the extra dimension in
the same sense that a rubber band could
be wrapped around my wrist you can wrap
the rubber band around your wrist if
it's an oriented rubber band you can
wrap it so that the arrows point this
way or so that the arrows point this way
so we have two kinds of wrapped strings
is a wrapped or while the correct term
is wound wound around a compact
direction here is one of them it comes
around the other side and it points that
way okay that's one the other one goes
in the opposite direction
let's take to wound strings like this to
wound strings like this and let me just
draw it a little differently
let's put do it this way
this one goes what can happen to to
wound strings which around in opposite
direction well remember the basic the
basic process of string theory is for
Strings to come together and join and
split now the rule is that when they
join and split orientation is remembered
a string like this and a string like
this can let's put some more orientation
arrows on it let's ask how they can join
they can join like that I don't think I
need words to describe it I think the
picture describes it well enough the
lines have to be or the arrows have to
be continuous okay what you can't have
is a string splitting somehow like that
here the line can't be continuous you
run into a contradiction as these points
come together alright so this is the
kind of thing that can happen the
opposite namely the time reversal of it
can also happen strings which are like
this can come together and join and so
forth
alright that's the basic phenomena of
splitting and joining and it's the thing
which is governed by a coupling constant
so what can happen here what can happen
is clear this can happen let's say oh I
lost track of the orientation
now it's not really wound anymore as
from the point of view of topology you
can unwind it into this all we've done
here is we've taken this we've stretched
it around and then joined it on the far
side to form the original wound pair
well we can undo that and now it's
unwound it's just a single unwound
string all right now one way to think
about it is to keep track of winding
number winding number can be defined to
be positive four windings which look
this way we'll call that winding number
one and it was wound the other way we'll
call it winding number - I won't try to
give you a mathematical definition but
winding it on my wrist if if the arrows
point this way we'll call that positive
winding if they point the other way
we'll call it negative winding if I have
a single string which is wound like so
what's the winding number the winding
number is +1 if I have another one
forget this one for the moment just
throw it over on the side we have
another one which is 1 this way that has
winding number -1 the two together all
together have winding number 0 this has
winding number 0 it's not 1 on the round
at all
so what's preserved is winding number
let's take another case let's imagine
now two strings which around the same
way there's two strings round the same
way what can happen to them they have
winding number two the sum of the two of
them have winding number two what can
happen well let's let's let's draw it
over here again
[Music]
these are going this way and they come
around here they're both going the same
way you can't unwind this you can do
something you can have a process of
splitting and joining which does this
which interconnects them a new way can
you see what I've drawn across them
we've crossed them but still after
they've crossed the arrows are still
continuous there's no contradiction in
the direction of the arrows
this also has winding number two you
learn if it's one string with winding
number two this is two strings each one
with winding number one each one with
winding number one but the sum total of
the winding numbers is 2 all right so
here's again another example winding
number is conserved you can't change the
winding number although you can change
the number of connected components so if
you have winding number 100 you could
have one string wound around a hundred
times you could have two strings each
round the same way 50 times you could
have a hundred strings each round once
and they can all communicate in the
sense that you can morph from one
configuration to the other but you can't
change the winding number so winding
number is an absolutely conserved
quantity in this kind of string theory
never can change let's let's forget why
let's come we're going to come back to
winding number two moment well maybe we
should discuss winding them yeah okay
this one over here that can just be
thought of as a tiny little particle
let's just think of it as a little
particle it's a string but it's a
particle what's it characterized by it's
characterized by components of momentum
ties by many things shape and all sorts
of other things but in particular let's
characterize it by its components of
momentum in particular the component of
momentum in the
in the this direction over here the
component of momentum in that direction
has to be an integer number that's
called in integer number of a quantum of
momentum and the quantum of momentum has
to do with the circumference let's just
call it the radius around here our
distance around here I'll call our it's
a circumference strictly but I'm just
going to call it R because R is the
standard term for it the quantum of
momentum in this direction and also
incidentally the quantum of energy in
that direction for matter if these are
massless if these are massless particles
energy and momentum are proportional to
each other for example if they were
gravitons if they were graviton moving
this way or this way the energy is also
them as also quantized in that unit and
so the energy of the momentum is the
momentum can have either sine it can be
plus or minus the momentum the energy is
always plus for the same amount n over R
it has momentum n over R and it has an
energy also n over R that's the these
are that's the energy due to momentum
and in particular momentum along the
small direction here it's quantized so
that's a that's unwound particles and
the contribution of energy due to
momentum
oh let's think about now what yeah
what is the momentum of a string moving
in space basically it's just the
velocity of the center of mass it's just
the velocity of the center just like a
rubber band just like a rubber band its
momentum is its mass density which for
simplicity we can take to be 1 times it
just its mass which we can take to be 1
for a rubber band times its velocity so
the velocity the momentum is
proportional to the velocity and we can
think of this as the X the tau tau is
the time variable that describes the
motion of the string in the quantum and
the simple quantum mechanics of we've
described previously and it's got to be
in integer multiples now let's think
about the wound strings the strings
which are wound around what is the
typical energy of a wound string well
strings have a certain tension let's
just work in units in which that tension
is one but tension is energy per unit
length so for energy per unit length if
there's a given energy per unit length
then the energy of a wound string is not
in / R but it's some other integer I'm
going to call the other integer W W
stands for winding number times R the
energy of a collection of strings which
are wound around here are the integer
winding number times R whereas the
energy of a string which is not wound
around the compact Direction is n
divided by R so I think we talked about
this last time but let's discuss it
again a little bit
let's suppose that our is very small all
right here we have the spectrum of the
strings which are not wound the
separation between the levels is large
large because one over R is large so it
looks like this with the separation
being of order 1 over R is N equals 0 is
N equals 1 and so forth now let's look
at the spectrum of the wound strings in
other words the energy levels of the
wound strings those also come in integer
multiples is 0 winding number one
winding number 2 winding number -1
winding number minus 2 but now it's W
times R so that means if R is large well
let's say R is large or I was smart I
think I said I was small what did I say
I said R is large or small or small okay
so that makes the separation large here
but it makes it very small here now
let's go to the other extreme I know
that we talked about this before but I
want to reiterate it again let's go to
the other extreme this is our much less
than some unit of length in string
theory the natural unit of length of
string theory let's just call it 1 is
are much bigger than 1 what do the
energy levels look like
well 4 are much bigger than 1 1 over R
is small and these excitations here are
very close together what about these
here R is very large so it takes a large
energy to wrap around
they look like this suppose all you knew
all you could measure about these
particles namely the things the social
I'm talking about the things associated
with the compact directions the only
thing that you can measure about the
compact directions let's suppose was the
energy of the particles and you're
trying to figure out what the radius of
compactification that's known as the
radius of compactification what is the
radius of compactification well your
problem is how do you tell the
difference between particles which have
energy with respect to the compact
direction because they have momentum or
because they have winding number you
can't obviously just from the energy
levels you can't tell so with this
particular spectrum there's an ambiguity
are you in the theory with a small
compactification in which large
separations between different momenta
small separations between different
winding number or are you in a world
with a very large radius of
compactification and in which the role
of winding number and momentum has been
interchanged you think well maybe you
can do a lot of other kind of
experiments maybe you could scatter
these particles together see what comes
off one of the very very remarkable
mathematical facts about string theory
is that the inability to tell which kind
of world you're in is rigorously correct
for everything that you can calculate
about these strings collisions between
them that that two different theories
with very different radii of
compactification if you interchange
winding with with let's call it with
momentum around the compact direction
the theories behave in exactly the same
way so conclusion arm
in certain sense it doesn't make sense
to think of the compactification as
smaller than a certain size there's a
certain size where they cross over and
where they interchange and if the size
of the compactification is smaller than
that it's just entirely equivalent to a
larger compactification with or with
winding and momentum integer does that
mean that the winding number is a
mathematical convenience rather than a
physical well I don't know what to say
it says that it says that that there's a
symmetry it says there's a symmetry and
that there's physicists use the term
duality which means an equivalence
between different descriptions of the
same thing is there are of interest for
these two things of the same in some
units it's R equals one and there you
have some extra special symmetry that
you go that not only can't you tell
which kind of theory you're in but you
can't tell which are which are which
yeah they're the same yes there is a
special point now I wrote an equation
over here that momentum is equal to the
X T tau let me make that a little more
precise every point on the string has a
motion in particular I'm thinking about
the motion around the compact direction
but different parts of the string could
could in principle be moving different
than other parts of the string ah no it
could be differentially moving in
different directions different there are
different speeds and so forth the full
momentum that we're talking about when
we talk about the momentum is actually
the sum of the momenta of all the little
bits of string
[Music]
give me the summit or you can think of
as an integral over the entire string of
the velocity the X D tau and we
checks am I talking about I'm talking
about why actually the one that goes
around the string dyd cow what about the
winding number
anybody got a mathematical expression
for the winding number imagine now a
string which is warmed simplest
possibility its wound around here this
is the y coordinate the y coordinate is
periodic it comes back to itself but the
string also has a sigma coordinate the
string also has a sigma coordinate and
that's embedded in the string if the
string is wound in this very simple way
there another way of saying it is that
Sigma is proportional to Y actually Y
divided by the total radius of
compactification I guess if Y comes back
to itself after going distance R and
Sigma comes back to itself over after
going around once then the right
relationship is that Sigma is y over R
it's just another way of saying that as
you go around Sigma as you go around the
rubber band the rubber band goes around
the Y direction well now look at this
let's look at the Sigma by dy that's
just 1 over R the Sigma by dy let's just
take the signal by with the Y the Sigma
by dy is proportional to the little
spacing between here and here and the
total winding number is the sum of a
little bit of the Sigma dy as you go
around
the string in other words the winding
number yeah actually this is right R
times this and the winding number I
believe is what I had an equation
where'd it go
[Music]
Y over R is equal to Sigma so the Sigma
by D Y is 1 over R is one of our the
total winding number is 1 over R times
the integral dy by D Sigma divided by
the Sigma
does this make sense that the total
winding number what's the integral of a
derivative what you started
usually the integral of a derivative in
lots of cases just plain zero if a thing
comes back to itself when you go all the
ways around but why doesn't go come back
to itself when you go all the ways
around Y itself changes by 2pi so the
integral dy DT Sigma is just a total
number of times that the string wraps
around that direction so this is kind of
curious t-duality this funny duality
between winding number and momentum is
equivalent to interchanging NNW
interchanging R and 1 over R and
interchanging the Y D tau with the Y D
Sigma funny mathematical construction
keep that in mind that t-duality
is interchanging winding and momentum
interchanging are with 1 over r and
interchanging the derivative of y that's
a position of the string dy D tau would
be y by D Sigma where ya dy by D tau
would be y by D Sigma the derivative
this is partial derivative it's pretty
abstract but this is an exact symmetry
of string theory if you make these
interchanges nothing changes it saves it
so I say once again if the symmetry is
dy/dt swap dyd town swap the yv tau for
the y by D Sigma now the reason I
introduced this will will see why I
didn't have to tell you this but I'm
telling you now because no is the
relationship it's just you interchange
them wherever is wherever you saw the
expression dy by D tau you replace it by
the expression might be Y by D Sigma
it's a weird thing to do but in all
observable quantities scattering
amplitudes energy levels all of the
properties of the string theory don't
change if you make those changes let's
talk about something else
yeah the stream don't want to land
around the DNI's there warn't anything
why we did it get in this nice stable if
it can be involved in the other step
forward somebody may hit this string
over here with some energy hitting it
with some energy among other things may
stretch it out in fact it may stretch
out to look like this
you blast it with a lot of energy I've
drawn a very neat configuration over
here of course but if I blast it with a
lot of energy it might be much more
complicated than that but still have
this kind of configuration now once
you've done that and you take into
account that the strings split and join
then this can separate itself into two
strings with opposite winding number
once you've created two strings with
opposite winding number that I'm no
longer connected they can separate from
each other they can separate from each
other and when they separate from each
other well then you've got an isolated
string with winding number one and
another one that you can just send off
the Alpha Centauri and never see it
again the answer is that in general you
cannot prevent it from happening you may
have to in particular if the distance
around here is large then it takes a
large amount of energy to create these
winding strings here it is the well
let's say we yeah
the energy the energy itself was
proportional to our four winding number
so with a small amount of energy it's
not going to happen you don't have
enough energy to stretch the string that
far but if you collide two strings with
a large amount of energy they splatter
all over the place they stretch out and
Wilder in the chaotic directions and
there's some probability that the that
they'll reconnect it will not change the
total winding number but it will take a
single string or perhaps two strings
which are not wild which collide with
each other and convert out of them
something with two strings of opposite
winding number once that happens they
can separate and they go off so the
answer is generally that that will
happen in collisions if you don't have
it that way to begin with the same
question occurs for electric charges if
you start with a neutral world
why are there electrons well even if
there weren't electrons or their got to
be something to start with is nothing
there's nothing but maybe you just
started with photons you take some
photons you collide them together and
what comes out is electrons and
positrons if you take the positrons and
you throw them away you don't throw them
away but you push them off to some
distant place you left with electrons
that's all so you you can't have you
can't forbid these things you can't
forbid them and eventually you will
create them now these winding numbers
and these momenta these momentum quantum
numbers is quantized momentum or not
only in some sense similar to electric
charge but they have all of the
properties of electric charge in
particular two strings of opposite
momentum one going around one I do this
let's see oh yeah I can do it - screams
going around the opposite way with
respect to the big dimensions of space
so here they are two strings these have
the same no these these have the same
winding number okay that's easy that's
this two strings are the same winding
number will repel I'll tell you why in a
moment two strings with opposite winding
number will attract what is this
attraction and repulsion this attraction
repulsion actually corresponds to the
gravitational attraction and repulsion
of the higher-dimensional theory if we
live in a world of let's say three
dimensions three space dimensions and we
add in one more tiny direction then
strings which are wound oppositely may
be in different places in the big
dimensions different places in space we
have a string wrapped this way we have a
string wrap that way
they'll attract each other if they have
opposite winding number I'll attract
each other in our ordinary
three-dimensional sense
likewise if they have the the same
winding number they will repel each
other so they behave like electrical
charges what colors where is electrical
or a repulsion and attraction come from
it comes from the electromagnetic field
and of course the electromagnetic fields
is deeply connected with photons and so
forth where does this attraction come
from and the answer is it comes from
gravitation but not gravitation in the
four dimensional sense but gravitation
in the five dimensional sense in the
extra dimensional sense in the theory
with extra dimensions the Einstein
gravity the extra dimensions manifests
itself in the phenomenon of attraction
between like momenta nope cross without
attraction between opposite momenta in
the compact direction and repulsion of
things with the same moment that's not
obviously easy to see I've told you this
before it's not it's not something I'm
telling you for the first time and in
fact you can relate it to Einstein's
field equations let's let's not going to
relate it to Einstein field equations in
any depth I'm just going to discuss the
origin of the electromagnetic field or
the analog electromagnetic field that's
associated with this electrical type
behavior of these particles there must
be something like an electric field
there must be something like a magnetic
field if they're behaving so much like
electrically charged particles what is
it
okay so first just ordinary Maxwell
equations the electric and magnetic
field are describable in terms of a
vector potential a four-dimensional
vector potential a
mooo you build up the magnetic field as
the curl of the vector potential and the
electric field as related to the time
derivative of the of the vector
potential it's a four vector it has four
components let's go to gravity in five
dimensions gravity is described by a
metric tensor the metric tensor let's
call it G M n why don't I use mu and nu
hey I'm saving mu and nu for the four
dimensions of ordinary space-time but
we're now talking about a five
dimensional world so let's use for the
five dimensional world
M&N but what a lemon in run over they
run over the ordinary dimensions of
ordinary space-time plus one more
direction so we can write out we can
write GM n as having various components
G mu nu that's the ordinary dimensions
and then g mu v v is v extra dimension
and then what else g55 those are the
components of the gravitational field
what about what about g v mu ro g mu v
what about g v mu symmetric tensors yeah
the same thing okay these are the
independent components of the
gravitational field in five dimensions
well this one here that's just a metric
of four-dimensional space-time so just a
usual einstein gravitational field
nothing new there he only have something
that has an index it has a five index
here but the five index is this hidden
direction we can't see it but it also
has a mew index which means that it's a
four vector we would mistake this
object for a four-vector it has four
components it's like a mule let's make
that identification because that's that
is the correct identification and what
about g55 that had that has no
components in the usual four dimensional
sense so it must be a scalar that scalar
is usually called Phi it's called a
dilettante or sometimes called a Dilla
time but it's almost always called Phi
what is g55 it's the component of the
metric around the fifth direction it
tells you how big the fifth Direction is
if g55 is big it's just a metric it's
the square of the distance around the
fifth Direction is what it is
if g55 is big the fifth direction is big
if g55 is small the fifth direction is
small the metric tensor in five
dimensions is a field it can vary from
place to place all of these things can
vary from place to place this is just a
usual gravitational field varying from
place to place this becomes an analogue
of the electromagnetic field which can
vary from place to place and this is a
scalar which can vary from place to
place but what does that scalar mean
that scalar is the size of the fifth
Direction that can vary from place to
place somebody asked me that before and
you can imagine waves in space where the
waves of space are not waves of
electromagnetism they're not waves of
gravity they're waves of varying size
for the fifth dimension okay but
nevertheless the quiescent ordinary
vacuum doesn't have such waves it's
fixed okay but in general the size can
vary from place to place okay this is an
electromagnetic field if this is an
electromagnetic field then it's also a
gravitational field and it's an analogue
electromagnetic field thought of as a
graphic
a tional field what are the sources of
gravitational field there are things
like energy and momentum in particular
the sources of mixed components of the
field like this are components of
momentum so the source of this component
of the gravitational field is actually
the momentum in the fifth direction the
flow of momentum in the fifth direction
that means that the source of this
analog vector potential is going to be
the component of momentum going around
the fifth direction lesson the momentum
quantum number the one where is it the
momentum quantum number over here can be
thought of as electric charge in an
analogue whit's on that and then the
Colusa klein theory in which the mew
five component of the gravitational
field is the electromagnetic field
electric charge momentum electric field
are component of the metric well good
that's easy that was easy
[Music]
that was easy
what about and of course go a little bit
further and we can say that that the
that the electric that the electric
field is associated with the graviton
with a graviton itself
okay now let's come to the winding
number
some saris feed and proportional to n or
no no n no n is an integer it's related
to our it's related to our it's not
quantized it's related to the size of
that dimension and it can vary from
place to place continuously and smoothly
called a Dilla Tom and it's a wave field
that string theory was right should
exist in some form or another but in any
case it's part of the mathematics of
string theory let's come to the winding
number now I told you that the winding
number also behaves with this property
that opposite winding numbers attract
are like winding numbers repel they also
behave like electric charges but not the
same kind of electric charge as the
momentum quantum numbers it's as if
there were two kinds of electric fields
two kinds of electromagnetism
living side by side two kinds of photons
two kinds of charges winding number
associated with something we could call
winding photons and a momentum quantum
number associated with momentum photons
but momentum photons are just a piece of
the gravitational field in other words
they're gravitons which are polarized
along the Meuse I've directed the field
what is the field or the analog of
photons which is emitted and absorbed by
winding number not by momentum of by
winding number then here we know the
answer we'd have to go back several
lectures for fairly early lectures but
let me remind you
this is probably something you've
forgotten I told you but I don't think I
stressed it very hard let's go back to
the spectrum of closed strings the
closed strings
what kind of states are there of closed
strings we start with the closed string
being totally unexcited and then what do
we do at it we excite oscillations on it
we excite oscillations with the creation
and annihilation operators which create
and excite waves on the string they're
not creation and annihilation operators
particles the creation and annihilation
operators for waves moving along the
string these are closed strings let me
just remind you what kind of operators
there are there are creation and
annihilation operators I won't think
I'll just think about creation operators
and I won't put a little plus because we
wind up with too many indices a creates
a unit of excitation what labels it well
first of all the A's are labeled by
directions of space directions of space
perpendicular to the momentum of the
object of the string so they're labeled
by directions of space let's call it I I
can equal if the string is going down
the z-axis it can be X it could be Y or
there can be X 1 X 2 or it can be a
compact direction Y so the eyes vary
over all the directions of space
including the ones which are wrapped up
that's one thing there now what's the
other index that depends on the
frequency of the oscillator and that was
an integer and it tells you how much
energy when you create one of these
oscillations creates an energy
proportional to n all right so n is
related to the frequency I is related to
direction in space
and one more thing you remember what it
was for closed strings would weather the
wave is propagating around the string
remember the string is oriented there's
little arrows whether the wave is going
one way around the string or the other
way around the string
I don't remember there's anybody
remember how we label the two let's just
call it left moving waves and right
moving waves a I in and left and right
here are purely symbolic they refer to
to the direction on the string not left
and right in real space okay now there
was a rule I told you the rule I called
it level matching it's a rule I'm not
going to go into the rule now I think I
explained it a little bit what it had to
do with but it's a rule and the rule is
the amount of energy and left room
moving waves must equal the amount of
energy and right moving waves that's a
fundamental rule of string theory the
mathematics goes to hell in a handbasket
a few threw violate it and so let's see
what kind of states we have we can first
of all have the state with no energy in
it at all
that's a tachyon it's not there in super
string theory but in the simple versions
of the string theory and it has minus
two units of energy we work that out -
two units of energy let's attack a bad
thing we don't want it what's the first
excitation what's the next energy up
well the next energy up is to hit it
with the lowest frequency oscillator to
excite one unit of energy with N equals
one so for example we could hit it with
a I I can be any one of the directions
of space one the lowest oscillator left
or a one i right oh but neither of these
states are a legitimate option and the
reason is because this one has one you
of left-moving energy and no units of
right-moving energy this one has one
unit of right moving energy and no units
are left moving energy and so it doesn't
satisfy this principle that the amount
of energy and left and right after
balance okay so these are gone they're
not there what's the next thing up the
next thing up is to apply two units of
the lowest oscillator one left and one
right to make sure that you have
balanced energy going and left and right
and that means a i1 left
times a j-1 right I and J are two
directions of space okay they are the
two directions of space for simplicity
let's imagine the directions of space
are the usual three directions of space
plus one more namely the v direction the
thing that I called Y here one more
direction of space the one more and we
apply this of course to the vacuum these
are the things we identified with
graviton and other massless particles
are with polarizations that have to do
with I and J well there is something new
when we add this v direction one or both
of these indices can now be in the v
direction earlier before we discuss the
v direction i and j could only be
ordinary directions of space and these
corresponding the gravitons which have
polarizations which are they're like
photons they're polarizations and the
polarization is characterized by two
directions of space but now we have
something new we can have AI be the
ordinary direction of space and this one
being the v direction of space the
internal direction the small direction
okay now we have something which has a
vector in
X the fresh direction here we don't even
call out a direction in space normally
and so it has the same kind of index
structure that a photon would have this
is like a photon it has a polarization
let's say moving down the z-axis this
could be polarized either X or Y or
however the many many dimensions we have
to worry about and this is very similar
to a photon now but there are two ways
to do it you could have this one being
left in this one being right or you can
have a i1 right a15 left oh there are
two possibilities now and it seems like
that means that there are two kinds of
particles that behave like photons that
are similar to photons the correct thing
to do is to add them and subtract them
in the sense of quantum mechanics -
linear superpositions but whatever there
is there's going to be two types of
objects which have the index structure
of a photon there's going to be two
kinds of photon fields the one with the
sum that's identified with ordinary
graviton moving down the z axis the
other one is identified with another
field a separate field that also has a
structure similar to photon and guess
what it is connected with it is the
field the electromagnetic like field
whose sources are what winding number so
one linear combination is associated
with momentum and one linear combination
is associated with a winding number
these two things one of them is
associated with gravitons which is which
are the field quanta of the
gravitational field and the other one is
associated with something called B mu nu
which is different than the graviton
different properties but also gives rise
it's mixed component is also like a
photon so here's what we can say now
what is T duality and this is a field
this is a field which exists in string
theory called the rom owned the Cobb
Ramon field not important what it's
called
it is another field which appears in
same here oh no no no no no wait a
minute both of these of our polarized
like photons there's one more nobody
asked me about what about a 5 5 a 5 a 5
left right that one's the one that
behaves like the scalar that's the one
associated whose field quanta these are
the field quanta of this one over here
okay
namely the radius of the of the compact
Direction here which was which would
correspond into the winding number the
other corresponding the one with a plus
sign corresponds to momentum and that's
the one that's associated with graviton
the one with the minus sign is
associated with with the winding number
yeah okay so now we have a more complete
idea of about t-duality
and involves momentum being interchanged
with winding number and involves are
being interchange with one over R it
involves replacing the X by the Sigma
with the X by D tau this is the integral
of this is winding number the integral
of this is momentum and finally it
involves interchanging g mu v with b mu
v
all right so these theories have
moisture though of course not clear that
the ordinary world does have such fields
we don't know of real particle
candidates for all these fields we don't
so this is at the moment a mathematical
construction and we're exploring a
mathematical construction there's lots
of ideas about how to use these these
constructions but at the moment I think
we should regard this as an exploration
of the mathematics of the theory there's
plenty of room in physics for these
objects incidentally but I don't want to
get into the phenomenology of them good
so there we are that's what t-duality is
after five minutes we're going to come
back and talk about T duality for open
strings and how it leads to a new
concept completely new concept called D
branes
so let's take a break yeah okay so we've
figured out what T duality is this very
strange interchange of big geometries
with small ones and various other things
going on I want to concentrate now on
the aspect of T duality that has to do
with well let's let's erase some
blackboard here ah
this one
now you're going to see the kind of
gymnastics that that the kind of
deductions that people have made over
the years the ste duality is one of them
they're implicit in the mathematics
there many of them are very surprising
we'll talk about d-branes and how one
was forced to have these new objects in
the theory which are called D branes D
stands for dearest lady rish lay had
nothing to do with him he was dead for
many hundreds of years this should be
called pea brains for polchinski but pea
brain was already a term in use brain is
spelled BR a in II like membrane and one
speaks of DN brains these stands for
darish lay not for the dimension of
space n stands for the dimensionality of
the brain a string is a one brain a
membrane is a two brain a solid
three-dimensional chunk which may be
embedded in higher dimensions but solid
through is is a three brain and so forth
so there's D in brain where do they come
from what do they do what's there what's
there they're not just made up things
they were essential to the consistency
of the theory the mathematics absolutely
demanded them and the result of knowing
about them has been to derive an
enormous number of equivalence between
different theories and in fact it turned
out that those enormous numbers of
equivalences turned out to be enormous
numbers of equivalences between
different kinds of geometric structures
equivalences which the mathematicians
have no idea existed equivalences
between different the calabi-yau
manifolds
and which the mathematicians were
entirely surprised by and they turned
out to be able to confirm them but this
is some of this is now part of the
gymnastics of string theory and the
brains have played an enormous leap
powerful role also in the applications
of it so let's talk about open strings
now d-branes have to do with open
strings open strings what's the winding
number of an open string open strings
don't have stable winding numbers if you
have an open string on a compact space
now this that this picture is sort of
shorthand for all of the compact
directions with of which there are
presumably six in super string theory
and all of the open uncompact directions
are but let's imagine now that in
addition to closed strings there are
open strings open strings now have
endpoints
we can't classify them with winding
number it doesn't make sense to classify
them with winding number they're not
wound so we have to we have to think
about what happens to them when we do
this process of treaty duality t-duality
was a phenomena discovered in closed
string theory but surprisingly it also
makes sense for open string theory and
I'm going to show you what it says
there's something rather remarkable
something which is confirmed in other
ways but this is the simple way to think
about it um there's a string an open
string and what are the rules for open
strings do you remember what the rules
are for what goes on at the end of an
open string the boundary conditions on
the end of an open string no I'm on no
I'm on the end of an open string should
satisfy the X or dy again this is y this
is X any of the coordinates
but let's step in particular well let's
write them them both the X by D Sigma
equals zero
dy by D Sigma equals zero and what does
that correspond to that corresponds to
the idea that the end of the string is a
string it's made up of a lot of tiny
infinitesimal mass points and supposing
the end of the string had some net
stretching the X by D Sigma was not
equal to 0 that would exert a force on
the very last molecule well as you
subdivide the molecules into smaller and
smaller structures to go to the
continuous limit of the string the
molecules get lighter and lighter and
lighter how much force can you put on a
mass on a thing of arbitrarily small
mass without having it accelerate with
an infinite acceleration the answer is 0
in the limit that means that the string
cannot afford to have any net stretching
at the end of the string so that that's
why that's where these conditions come
from the X by D Sigma dy by D Sigma
should be equal to 0 and that's the
forbid infinite accelerations either in
the X direction or the Y direction of
course there is another possibility and
that's somebody holding the end of the
string and applying an enormous force so
to keep it from moving but nobody is
standing there holding the end of the
string then if there's any net tension
in the end of the string it will
accelerate infinitely top to basically
to remove that stretching ok now what
about t-duality let's suppose now that
this was a small compact direction and
we want to replace the theorems very
very much smaller extremely small we
want to say laden that this is supposed
to be equivalent to a theory with a
large compact direction here's the large
compact collection enormous lis large
could be cosmologically large
what do I do with these open strings
okay
well was supposed to replace winding
number by momentum but remember that
momentum was what was momentum related
to it was related to DX by D tau right
velocity what was winding number related
to the X by D Sigma namely exactly what
goes on here I should actually write
since I'm mostly interested in the
compact directions for the moment let's
concentrate on the compact Direction
t-duality involves among other things
replacing every place you see it be Y by
D tau by the expose or dy by D Sigma by
dy by D tau so what does it say then
about open strings open strings when you
replace where when they undergo this
process of t-duality what you have to do
is you have to change the boundary
conditions and the boundary conditions
at the end of the string become the X by
D tau equals 0 or in this case we're not
sorry
the t-duality is associated with the
compact directions we don't want to do
that only the compact directions are
being interchanged small with large
we're not diddling at all with the
uncompact Direction one compact
Direction Y goes why the radius in the Y
Direction becomes big all right roll was
we were supposed to replace the Y by D
Sigma but dy by D tau if strings
originally moving on the surface had no
mam boundary conditions that's dy by D
Sigma equals 0
after t-duality they have diversely band
rican
what does it mean to say that the Y by D
tau is equal to zero Oh incidentally
this is only at the endpoints this is at
the ends of the string
it means the endpoints are forbidden
from moving so wherever they started
they are stuck at where are they stuck
well wherever they're stuck there's
something holding them there it means
that this theory has objects in it which
can nail down the ends of strings there
are strings
there must be if T duality is to make
sense
there must be objects in the theory
which can nail down the ends of strings
you start with a theory with no such
object and the strings just move freely
and after T duality you discover there's
some kind of object in the theory which
has nailed down the location of the
string it's nailed down only the Y
component we have not played around with
the X's the X's are still free to move
the compact direction here is now nailed
down so where is it nailed down let's so
here's a little space
that's nailed down someplace someplace
in Y Y goes around this way let's put
that place right over here there's
something here which is capable of
holding the ends of strings nailing them
down that object is called a D brane D
federa Schley and it wasn't put in by
hand instead one asked what if there are
open strings in a theory and the theory
has t-duality
which it must have for reasons that are
by now well understood then what happens
to the open strings when you interchange
the small compact direction for the
large compact direction and the answer
is that you discover something new you
discover some new kind of object which
it's holding narrow she's not yeah Oh
does it necessary that the y-value be
the same for the two implants no I think
you're asking whether this can bend
I drew it so that it oh yeah yeah yeah
yeah I could that's right but the
simplest cases where where it's just
fixed fixed in some and some position
now what position can you do you put it
out here here here well the answer is
that you better be able to put it
anywheres
so therefore this has to be a movable
object because there was nothing special
about one point in space than the other
point in space along these axes so
there's got to be a movable object which
functions as a anchor point for the ends
of strings if it's movable then you can
be more quite sure that it's also
bendable our relativity can't make sense
with absolutely rigid objects and so it
will also be bendable but let's just not
bend it for the moment and strings can
attach themselves to it though strings
attached to it can exist a string can
come or let's let's so the good that's
that's a these are called d-branes right
this is the first of all supposing we
took let's let's take an example
supposing we took 10 dimensional string
theory which has nine dimensions of
space nine dimensions of space and we
made one of them compact and then
introduced a D brane in this way what
would be the dimensionality of the
d-brane
we'll be 1:9 no eight-eight we've pinned
down one direction and left the other
nine the other eight directions of space
free to move around all right here's a
tabletop that tabletop is 2-dimensional
if there's an object attached to the
tabletop
how many directions is free to move in
and how many is it constrained in it's
free to move in two directions here's a
string here's a string with two ends or
my finger is at end of a string it's
free to move in two directions and
constrained in its third Direction all
right so if I constrain one dimension if
I constrain one dimension it creates for
me in 3-dimensional space a
two-dimensional surface supposing them
now in nine dimensions of space and I
constrain the end of a string I
constrain one of the dimensions it
becomes an eighth dimensional surface
that the string can move around now
suppose there was no reason for only
constraining you can do the same thing
with any number of compact directions
you can play this t-duality game with
any subset of the compact directions you
can play that's it's the same game and
you can in the same way construct
d-branes which pinned down any number of
the coordinates at the end of a string
can move in all right so let's take
three-dimensional space again let's
suppose now we've played this game and
we've constrained the vertical position
by doing this t-duality trick with
respect to the vertical direction
supposing I also do it now with respect
to the front-to-back
direction I could strain the motion of
the position at the end of a string so
it's constrained
vertically and this way that means that
the end of the string has to move along
the the intersection of this plane with
that plane so if I constrain two
dimensions what kind of brain am i
talking about a D in this case D one but
if I started with seven there with nine
dimensions of space seven
so each constraint removes a direction
that it's free to move in all right all
right for that reason you can have in
nine dimensions by playing this game
over and over again with the different
directions associated with a compact
space you can have the eight brains the
seven brains the six brains all the ways
down to what's the maximum number that
you can you can just get rid of the
freedom to move in any of the directions
of space then what does e then what
would you call the brain these 0d0 it's
a point or it's a point in space that
the string is connected to and it's not
free to move along any of the directions
that's a d0 brain the zero zero
dimension means a point you're going to
from the zero brains to the eight brains
they all make sense and they're all
their existence in some sense is all
necessary to the consistency of the
theory these zero brains are a new kind
of particle an unexpected new kind of
power
yes no no no not really no no um no no
[Music]
you couldn't no I'll show you why in a
moment I'll show you why in a moment
right okay we've played this game with a
compact directions but now let's imagine
having done this operation let's imagine
shrinking and shrinking and shrinking
this until it becomes arbitrarily small
what happens on this side it gets bigger
and bigger and bigger okay
so eventually on this side it can be so
big that it's completely mistaken for a
non compact for a non compact dimension
in other words if a dimensional space is
big enough for all practical purposes it
becomes a non compact what we've
demonstrated by this series of arguments
is that even in the non compact
directions
there must be objects which are the
anchors of strings they can be oriented
along compact directions they can be
oriented along non compact directions
any number of them and of any
dimensionality starting with zero and
going up to eight dimensions actually
you can go up to nine dimensions but
that means they completely fill space
and that simply means that we're talking
about open string theory in which the
open strings are just free to move but
they're not intraday we wouldn't call
them brains there are things that people
called D minus 1 brains but you don't
want to know they're not there they're
not real concept ok so you start here's
a d0 brain it's a point in space and a
string in can end on it where's the
other end of the string it could be on
another d0 brain
or it could be stretched out to infinity
that's not a good thing because it
becomes infinitely massive or it could
even come back to the same point the
same deep brother the same d-brane
that's a d0 brain what's the next one up
a d1 brain the one brain something very
interesting about it b1 brain it's a
line now as you already pointed out it
does not have to be a straight line we
deduce their existence in this way but
once we know that they exist and once we
know we're talking about a relativistic
theory they have to be bendable if
they're bendable they can even bend
around on themselves are there
structures which are physically physical
objects and they have strings connected
to them but now let's forget the strings
that are connected to them and the
strings connector and could be like this
let's forget the strings that are
connected to them and just look at them
this is a one-dimensional object it's
called a d1 brain it's a one-dimensional
object it can bend what's another name
in fact it can not only bend but it can
even come back on itself what's another
name for one-dimensional objects like
this strings but are they the original
strings no they are not the original
strings they're called d1 brains and
they're distinct from the original
strings how would you expect they might
be the same
that's the same all the way around II
got points on them to have articles and
points that don't I mean you have
streets that are attached on placing
well I may or may not have strings
attached to them but let's go through
our moment suppose they don't have
strings attached to them they're much
heavier in string that makes a lot of
sense because well how do they start out
they started out as anchors like
infinitely heavy things that could that
could hold the strings down but they're
not really infinitely heavy there
they're there their mass depends on some
coupling constants and so forth depends
on various things they're heavy they're
much much heavier than the ordinary
strings and so in that sense they're
anchors but they are string like
the TQ le hold for this one what sir the
t-duality holds my friends yeah
they also if it holds for the brains too
yeah it does hold for the brains ah
what's the next one up a D to brain a D
to brain is called the membrane
membranes I mean the two brains and
those are simply sheets like the table
top here that string ins can move around
on a pairs of strings can move around on
them like that these are the two brains
next one up the three brains in a
three-dimensional world a d3 brain fills
all of this filled space alright or
filled space into space filling brain
people and then the words to space and
if we had a d3 brane then that would
simply mean that we can have open
strings that can just move around they
have to be attached to the brain but the
brain is everywhere and so it's just
open strings that are free to move
around everywhere so it's often said
that ordinary open string theory is
string theory on a space-filling brain
but if we're living in a world with
higher dimensions then a three brain
doesn't fill all of space it's like a
two brain in the 3-dimensional space
it's a surface and strings can move on
it okay that's the idea of d-branes and
as I said and as I emphasized they are
mathematically important to string
theory but they also are the origin of a
lot of applications of string theory so
let me very quickly tell you what's
known you can start with one of these D
branes
I shouldn't the unconstraint directions
that are left over contact directions as
well yes yes yes that's correct but
that's certainly correct right okay
let's imagine a d-brane and I'm going to
draw it as a d2 brain there's the d2
brain now you know if you say to
yourself this is awfully slick though I
really believe that this has to be not
from the arguments that I made obviously
there's giving you some some sketches of
arguments whether string theory is the
Right theory of nature is not the issue
here
the mathematics of this is very very
tight by now I mean many many
cross-checks many many different things
point in the same direction mathematical
theorems that have come out of it though
the mathematical speculations have been
confirmed in mathematics so it's it's
remarkable and presumably correct ah all
right
here's an empty D brain think of it as
empty empty means it has no strings
ending arm it think of it as empty and
think of it as an empty space time or
empty space the space now is not the
full space but it's just a surface in
space but think of it as a space it's
empty we can put things into it we can
put strings into it like this little
open strings and these open strings are
free to move around now I'll tell you
what the what the basic process of them
is the basic thing they can do is their
endpoints these are oriented strings so
they have arrows associated with them
when the end points come together
in string theory let's say the end
points come together if we have two end
points one with an arrow coming into it
and the other with an arrow coming out
of it it can do the obvious thing namely
the end points come together and lift
off the surface and form a single string
with two end points like that how do we
think about that if these strings like
this are thought of as particles which
are free to move around and in string
theory particles or strings these are
very much like the original open strings
that we started with if we think of them
as particles which are constrained to
move on the surface or very close to the
surface then what we discover is that
these particles can split and join two
of them can come in join into one one of
them can go out join separate into two
we're starting to build up something
that looks like particle processes we're
starting to build up something that
looks very much like finding diagrams
two of them come in join to form one
maybe it hangs around there for a while
and then the reverse process happens and
it becomes two again we're building up
the kind of processes that quantum field
theory describes creation and
annihilation of particles transmutation
of the number of particles and so it
mean it's not completely surprising that
the mathematics of the interactions
between these particles looks very much
like quantum field theory in fact at low
energies where you don't have enough
energy to really excite the vibrations
of the strings
it is simply quantum field theory where
the particles of the quantum field
theory of these open strings in fact the
open strings behave like photons moving
around on the surface then enough
photons
the sense of the 10 dimensional theory
their photons in the sense of a theory
which lives and whose particles live
only on the surface that's the basic
connection between brains and their
application and studying quantum field
theory our brains like this define
quantum field theories and they define
quantum field theories in exactly the
way that I've just described but yeah
let some incidentally these are these
open strings connected to the brain here
do behave like photons moving around in
the brain they behave like photons in
the lower dimensional theory but let's
imagine now that we have more than one
brain there's no reason why you can't
have several brains for example parallel
to each other here's two brains parallel
to each other you can move them closer
and closer until they touch in which
case they just form a compound brain or
you can leave them separated let's leave
them separated for a moment let's put
three of them in just for fun three
parallel brains like that and let's
think of a kind of excitations that can
move around on them well you can have
and the excitations means ordinary
strings an ordinary string let's give
them names let's give the three brain
the three of the the three of these
names the names I'm going to give them
are red green and what yellow blue sorry
blue blue red green and blue this is
just the names of the three brains
of course we get that four or you could
have seven or we could have 15 but I'm
particularly interested in having three
of them for the moment what kind of
strings do we have we can have strings
which begin on red and end on red all
remember these strings are also oriented
keep in mind that they're oriented and
so what would you call this string I
would call it a red anti red or a red
red string this is a red red string and
therefore some kind of red red particle
we can also have red green particles
where green particles and ones let's
look like this where one end begins on
read the other beer end and the other
ends on green so what do we have what
are the class of particles we have we
have particles that are labeled by two
indices two colors for the case of three
brains we have three distinct colors and
we have particles which are labeled by
pairs of colors one associated with the
outgoing and the other associated with
the incoming does it sound like anything
you've seen before gluons gluons and
quantum chromodynamics
[Music]
of course maybe you should keep in mind
that this is embedded in a higher
dimensional space so to mimic that let's
think of lines in higher dimensional
space now there's no problem in going
from here to here or from here around to
here you're worried about passing
through here well we have there there
will be some rules there will be some
rules and the basic rule what is the
basic rule is really only one rule but
we can use it over and over again I'm a
red green string what can it do if it
hits a red red string
all right let's suppose this is going
out here and coming in here let's
suppose this is going let's see what I
want to have I want to have in here and
out here okay what can happen
this end can join with this end they can
come together and join and form a single
string which goes all the ways from here
to here in other words the red ant I
read the thing coming into red and the
thing going out of red one in one out
can join and simply make a single string
this is very much like a pet like a
green red gluon coming together with a
red red glue on and forming another red
green blue on same rules exactly the
same rules as for gluons but the string
cannot annihilate or lift itself off the
the surface on the other hand if we had
this situation here then these can come
together and they can lift themselves
off the surface
that's incidentally why there are eight
gluons instead of nine because one
linear combination can disappear and it
is not stable so the mathematical rules
for splitting and joining are exactly
the yang-mills quantum chromodynamics
rules for gluons
okay what about quarks okay so now what
about quarks what is a quark in this
language a quark in this language only
has one color
it's either a quark or an anti quark it
only has one color it doesn't have three
colors I'm sorry it doesn't have two
color and anti color color a quark must
be a thing which only has one end a
quark in this language is a string which
ends on one of these brains and goes off
to infinity now it doesn't really have
to go off to infinity it could go off to
some distant brain of a different kind
but it doesn't have another end which
ends on one of the
three that's a quirk and it's either a
string coming in or a string going out
when a string coming in and a string
going out meet each other they can join
and just disappear out into the off the
brain they can join and disappear from
the brain that's annihilation of a quark
and an antiquark if there's two quarks
they can't annihilate they they're stuck
there and that's just that's exactly the
same rule as quarks the mathematical
structure of the field theory that
described these strings moving around is
essentially exit with some little extra
added ingredients because of
supersymmetry it's a super symmetric
version of quantum chromodynamics and it
is a part of the reason that brains are
interesting for exploring quantum
chromodynamics I'm not going to show you
how they used in detail I'm just showing
you what the connection between things
is
[Music]
let's suppose there's only one brain
then it's not like quantum
chromodynamics what do you think it
might be like now we have objects we
don't have to name them red red green
blue it's just it's just a string it's
like well it's like quantum
electrodynamics it has only photons it
doesn't have this complicated gluon
structure these will be photons and what
would these things be charged electrons
they could be coming in or they could be
going out in which case there would be
electrons and positrons when two of them
come together they can annihilate one
last point which is really quite
fascinating
remember I told you that there are
ordinary strings and D strings these
strings were these no objects that we
discovered these no objects which are a
good deal heavier but there are also
strings an interesting question is can a
D string also end on a brain like this
incidentally I'm thinking about three
brains because I'm thinking about three
I'm thinking about mimicking
three-dimensional space the three brains
so these are really the three brains
interesting question can a D string
these string is itself something that
ordinary strings can end on but let's
forget that can a D string end on a
three brain a d3 brane the answer is yes
I'm not going to try to prove that for
you that's a much more elaborate
question but then if ordinary strings
the ones we started with make
electrically charged particles what do D
branes would be strings make that their
ends when they intersect the the three
brain here can you guess hmm
No well they're in some sense the true
but they are they got to be something
which is similar to what happens when
ordinary strings and magnetic monopoles
remarkable the magnetic monopoles are
much heavier than the electrons because
these strings are much heavier magnetic
monopoles are expected to be much
heavier than electrons they become
magnetic monopoles the relation between
magnetic monopoles and electrical
monopoles in in quantum electrodynamics
is mimicked by the relation between
these strings ending on these things and
ordinary strings on it so I've told you
a lot of stuff I don't expect that that
you're going to follow every detail but
I'm trying to show you how string
theorists discovered it took a long time
to make I mean that this didn't happen
all in one day this happened over a
period of twenty years basically or more
no more than most twenty years
twenty-five almost thirty years that all
these pieces were put together by
various people a very wide variety of
people who saw these connections and
today string theory and it's description
and time in terms of brains is the
primary tool for studying quantum
chromodynamics it's very bizarre the
whole thing made a full circle it made a
full circle from a theory of hadrian's
to a theory of quantum gravity to the
presence of d-branes there was
necessarily there which when you put
them together in the 10 dimensional
space put together three-dimensional
d-branes all of a sudden becomes the
theory of
of quantum chromodynamics that we that
it started out as so that's I don't know
what to describe it I describe it as
sort of mental gymnastics but I think
it's more than that I think it's a
process of discovery and unraveling of
the of the mathematical structure of
this thing it has wide application to
quantum chromodynamics other quantum
field theories fluid dynamics all kinds
of things so far it has not had
application to a direct application to
understanding the particle spectrum and
that's probably because it's just too
complicated yeah
what determines which of the dimensions
that t-duality is applied to you oh you
can do it any dimension you please to
any compact dimension you please choose
one that's convenient but that
eventually just winds up saying that
these d-branes can lie along any axis
and what chooses it history of the
universe
it's a membrane for magnetic monopoles
men magnetic monopoles 3 3 D 3 the
universe here from our point of view is
a three brain here d3 brane but if from
some of the other 10 dimensions which
the people who live on this world don't
even know about but a string ends over
here and happens to be a D string
they'll experience that as a magnetic
monopole
so something's these D strings arranged
as well what's that they must be wearing
these jeans are also oriented absolutely
you know they're also oriented you used
two planes for su - yeah and how do you
get the feature word it's not the
pleasure in other words su - if you have
a reflected University physics doesn't
work the same way
oh you come back charge conjugation
violation you're saying I don't really
drunk talking about the left-handed and
right-handed for particle/anti-particle
more interesting yeah there are answers
string theory certainly has a potential
possibility to describe that but not at
this level at this level you need when
you have khalaby on manifolds they can
have more complicated a symmetries that
allow that this toroidal
compactification doesn't allow it
there's a lot there are many many other
objects in the theory which I haven't
gotten into this is these are the
simplest to describe there are lots of
other constructions and other kinds of
objects that the theory has to have and
some some of them when they intersect
other ones break various symmetries and
we can probably we can discuss them some
other time I'm out of time and out of
energy and amount of momentum
[Music]
[Applause]
for more please visit us at stanford.edu